hey guys I'm pretty excited about this
one you know the three four five
triangles that we see everywhere three
four five triangles show up all over the
place in the SAT and high school
geometry courses even construction
workers use three four five triangles to
make sure that runes are built square
but there's something else special about
three four five triangles and I
genuinely think this is going to blow
some people's minds if you inscribe a
circle inside of any of those three four
five triangles guess what the area of
this circle is it's exactly Pi or Pi
unit squared do you want to see the math
first let's find the center of this
circle and from the center to this point
of tangency let's draw a radius and
let's do the same thing for this point
of tangency so radius will always be at
right angles to the tangent line and
same thing for this one to this tangent
line and this forms a quadrilateral and
since we have three right angles the
fourth one has to also be a right angle
we have two adjacent sides congruent
that means this whole quadrilateral is a
square so this side will also be R and
this side will also be R this entire
side is three and this Porsche question
is are this last piece is going to be 3
minus r and the same thing here this
base has a length of 4 and this portion
of it is R which means the remaining
part is going to be 4 minus r now let's
gray out everything except for the
circle and these two tangent lines if
you have the intersection of two tangent
lines of a circle the distance from here
to here is equal to the distance from
here to here so this will also be 3
minus r and same thing down here these
two tangent lines are intersecting at
this point which means this is going to
have the same distance as this so this
will also be 4 minus r and let's focus
on the hypotenuse we have this portion
here which is three minus r plus this
portion here which is 4 minus r and
that's all going to be equal to the
whole thing which was 5. now we can
solve for R let's subtract 3 from both
sides and let's subtract 4 from both
sides these threes will cancel each
other out these fours will cancel each
other out and we have negative R minus r
which is negative two R and then to
figure out the right hand side we can
combine the negative 3 minus 4 to get
negative 7 and 5 minus 7 is negative 2.
now to solve for R we can divide both
sides by negative 2 and that gives us
our radius equal to one and this is
definitely important let's put a box
around it so now let's clean up this
triangle let's bring it back to the
three four five triangle and we want to
find the area of the inscribed circle of
this 345 Triangle Well the area of a
circle is pi r squared and then we could
plug in 1 for this R and then 1 squared
is just one and then multiplying by 1
doesn't do anything so we know that the
area of this circle is equal to Pi and
this is true for every three four five
triangle how exciting